In this unit,
we're going to describe arc, a proposed,
a architecture for an assembler.
You've already seen the basic algorithm,
the basic logic of what
an assembler needs to do, but
now we need to translate that into a real
program and think about its architecture.
Now the truth is an assembler
is a pretty simple program.
And those of you who've already had
significant programming experience can
probably ignore this unit very safely and
just go ahead and write the assembler.
For those of you that has likely
less experienced programming,
you may want to look and remember our
suggestions for reasonable architecture,
reasonable components of an assembler.
Again, this is only a recommendation, you
may want to look at the recommendation and
then do whatever you feel
most comfortable with.
So let us see what is the types of modules
that probably will be useful when you
write an assembler, the type of operations
that need, certainly need to be done.
Well, three of them can be very easily
identified, so let's talk about them.
One of them is basically the parser,
something that is able to read a file and
get the different commands in it,
and breaks them into parts.
That's the first part reading and
parsing command, you will need to do that,
that's one thing.
Another a, part of the code probably
will have to actually understand
how you convert a mnemonic,
an assembly language command or
part of an assembly language
command into actual code.
So that we'll have to understand
the mapping and that's a different another
part that we'll need to be done somewhere
probably in your, an assembler.
And of course, there's another part that
we'll need to be able to handle symbols,
the symbol table itself.
So let's talk a bit about these
three different components and
once we talk about them,
you'll see that the rest of the program
using these different components,
which we think about as classes.
Eh, and, writing the complete program,
there is not much left to dap,
to be be done.
So let's start with the first part,
reading and parsing command.
The most important thing that we have to,
to to think about,
what we don't need to worry in this part.
So the whole point of the parser, of the
component that reads in parse command, it,
it only needs to be able to read
the input and break it into its parts.
It doesn't need to understand anything.
It doesn't need to understand
what the commands mean.
It doesn't need to understand how
they're translated to machine language.
It doesn't need to understand
the symbols or their addresses.
The only thing that needs to understand
is the format of the input language.
And how it breaks into
different components.
So let us now see what
are the different things,
what are the different actions
that it does need to worry about.
So let us see what are the things
it does need to do.
Well, first of all, it needs to be
able to read a file with a given name.
So, it needs to start being
able to start reading a file.
So, in particular, for example, you may
want, if you implement it as a class in
some programming language,
you may want a constructor to actually eh,
be able to accept the file name and
then open the file for reading.
So, you will need to know
how to handle text files,
how to read text files in the languages
that you're implementing.
[INAUDIBLE] The second thing is
once you've started reading a file,
you should be able to, every time,
get the next command in the file.
So getting the next command, if you look
at it, what does it mean in terms of
methods, operations that
this part would have to do?
Well you'll probably first have to know
whether you finished the file already,
are there more commands or
have you reached the end of the file?
And then you'll need to be able
to read into some kind of line,
into some kind of string,
the next command in the file.
So the kinds of things, so what that
entails is basically you will need some
kind of string eh, capability, string
handling capability and you will need
to know how to read line by line or
something like that in your language.
The third thing you will
have to know how to do,
is to basically break the command that
you just read into its components.
First of all, you need to know
what kind of command is it.
In our language, we have A-commands and
we have C-commands And
also, there are pseudo-commands
if you wish, that define labels.
These are not really commands in the sense
of being translated to machine language,
but for assembler,
it will have to basically know that here
we have a label definition,
so we couldn't handle it.
So that will be another,
third if you wish, pseudo-command,
that our assembler will have to know.
Once we know that, we will probably
want to give the rest of the program
easy access to the different
parts of the command.
So for example, in the assignment command,
we'll probably want to give access to
the destination part of the command,
to the computation part of the command,
and to the jump part of the command.
Similarly, in the label or an A-command,
we'll just want to give our user access to
the actual string, which may be a symbol
and may be an actual number that provided.
For example, the following set of a, a,
of method, if you wish, in a Java or
C-like, in a Java-like language, probably
would give you this type of access.
Eh, but eh, of course the whole point,
the important thing is that you get
the pieces of information separately and,
in any way that you wish
that one wants to provided.
The next thing that we have to do, is the,
is translate each one of the components of
the command into the actual ma,
machine code into the binary code.
Now we call that the specif,
specification of the language basically,
we have each part of the assembly
language command has a separate
part inside the bits of the machine
language command that correspond to it.
And this is basically what we
need to do this translation.
Now again, the important point is
what we don't need to worry about.
We don't need to worry about it all.
The, the way that our mnemonics,
the pieces of this code of,
of the command were obtained.
We only get a destination, for example, D.
Or a computation, for example,
M plus 1, and need to be able to translate
that very short string into the code.
We don't need to worry
about how we got it,
what part of the input line it is and
so on.
So this is a very low,
this is a very well-defined and
small task that we need to do now, and the
way to do it was really already specified.
How do we, for example,
translate the destination part into
the three bits that specify it?
Well there was a little
table that already appeared
in the previous lecture that
specified that translation.
For everything that can happen there,
for every string
that can be part of the destination,
we know what are the bits are.
So we just need to be able to do this
translation that's written in the table.
Similarly, there was another table
to specify the jump location.
And yet another table, the biggest one, to
specify how you take the computation and
translate it into the seven bits,
one of them called A and
the other one called C, that specify
the computation in the machine language.
And recall again,
that our machine language that is
a C-command actually starts with 31 bits.
So we also need to put the 31 bits, and
voila, we have our,
our machine language code.
So let us use an,
see an example how to use this parser eh,
object, and the code object to
actually do that translation.
So our parser object, presumable eh, gives
us access to each one of the parts, for
example the computation destination and
jump parts, so
we basically take each one of them and
ask the parser to give us the string that
corresponds to each part of these pieces.
Once we have these three
different strings,
we actually go to the code object and
ask them to translate
each one of them separately
according to the table it has in it.
So now, each part of these now we have the
machine code for each one of these parts.
To put them together,
we simply concatenate all of them
together with the three ones
that appear on the left.
And here we have a simple piece of code
that actually gives us the complete
translation of our original string
that held an assembly language command
into a string that now holds binary bits.
Let us now move into the third part
that we've already identified,
the symbol table.
The actual table that keeps
the association between symbol names and
their addresses.
Again, the important thing is what
the symbol doesn't have to understand, it,
it doesn't need to understand anything
about the machine language or
assembly language about
what the symbols mean.
The only thing that, the only thing that
our symbol table will have to understand
is maintain association
between a symbol and
a memory address, that is it,
without understanding anymore than that.
So, in particular,
what kind of the operations that must
our symbol table be able to handle?
Well, we probably need to create
a new empty symbol table.
We need to be able to add assemble
address pair to the table,
we need to able to look up into the table
and see, does this symbol exist there and
if so, what is the address there?
And these are the operations that
basically we need to, to be able to do.
So eh, that's very, very simple and most
languages already have a class that does
this kind of a symbol table for us, and
we'll probably just need to use it.
But let us look a little bit,
how are we going to use the symbol table?
So, here is the basic logic of
handling the symbols in our program.
We start, we will probably want to start
with creating an empty symbol table.
Then, if you remember in the hack machine
language, in the hack assembly language,
there are a bunch of pre-defined symbols.
Such as keyboard and so on.
So, we'll probably, the first thing we'll
probably just want to do in our program
is add all these pre-defined
symbols to the table.
Then, as we go reading the program and
translating it, we'll probably want to eh,
add labels and add variables to the,
a symbol table whenever we see it.
And then when you, we already have this
updated table all the time in our program.
Whenever we see an A-command
with a symbol in it,
we basically look up the new symbol,
look up the symbol in the table and
have a direct translation to a number
that then we can keep on eh, handy.
So the only thing that we probably need
to look a little bit more carefully
is how do we put
the symbols into the table.
How do we put the labels and
the variables into the table.
So let us look at that piece
a little bit eh, more carefully.
So in the case of a label, whenever we see
a label command inside parenthesis then
we probably need to add set label, to add
a symbol, into the, into the symbol table.
And what is the address
that's associated with it?
We probably need to know,
we need to remember what is the current
address that we're going to put
the next command in the file.
And that is the address that's
going to be associated with it, and
this is what we need to put
to add to the symbol table.
Now two comments are in place here.
Eh, one of them is, remember that this,
we need to know where we
are in the program, so
we need to keep on maintaining a running
line number, if you wish, in the table
specifying what is the address that every
new address is going to be put into.
Because this is exactly what is going to
tell us, what is the current address.
The second eh, comment is that you re,
if you recall eh, we probably want
to have a first pass, because there are
could be forward eh, references to labels.
We probably want to have a first pass and
enter all the labels
in a first pass into the symbol table
before we actually start using them.
Now for variables,
the situation is a slightly different.
Whenever we see another a,
label, another A-command
with a new variable that we don't
recognize yet, then first of all we know
it's not the label because the labels were
already all entered in the first part.
Then, if it's not in the symbol table,
it means that we have a new variable name.
And then we need to allocate
it the next available address.
And recall that the next,
the address that we allocate
the variables start at the number 16.
And then keep on going 17, 18, and so on.
So whenever we see a new, a, a new symbol
in an A-command, what we'd need to do is
allocate a new place for that new symbol,
enter, and enter it into the table.
So up to this point,
we've described three basic components
that our assembler will have to use.
And now let's see how do we use them.
What is the overall
logic of our assembler?
Well, we started by initial, initializing,
we need to initialize our parser to start
opening the file, we need to initialize
the symbol table to be empty, and
to start eh, having in it all
the pre-defined symbols, and so on.
And then we need to have our first
pass where you go after the program,
only pay attention to labels, and
enter them into the symbol table.
Then we have to restart reading
the program from the beginning,
read the command and translate it.
Read the command and translate it.
As we do that, we need to keep on
entering new symbols into the table,
only variable symbols now because
already all the label symbols
were already entered in the first pass.
And then our main loop is very simple.
You read one, you,
you read a command from the input.
If it's an A-command and we have a,
and we have a la, we have a symbol,
we need to translate that symbol into
an address as we've already described.
If it's a C-command, we need to split it
into the three parts that a C-command has,
translate each one of
them into binary code.
And then we have the binary
code to output for the, to,
to output as our output for
that line in the file.
And we keep on doing that
until the program is over.
And that's basically
a simple piece of code,
left to right, after we have the three
models that we've previously described.
So, what the, that finishes the basic
architecture, our, our suggestion for
basic architecture of an assembler.
And what we're going to describe in
the next unit is the basic mechanics of
doing the project of how to test it,
how to submit and so on.